Guide to the Americans For Immigrant Justice Records, 1982-2011 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
- Immigrants and Refugees Series, 1980-2004, (14 boxes)
  - Haitians Subseries, 1981-2004
    - U.S. Department of State responses to congressional inquiries regarding Haitian refugees, 2002
    - Regarding U.S. Haitian policy, 1993
    - YMCA Houston, 1994
  - Other Files Subseries, 1980-2002
    Files contain documents related to issues of deportation, asylum, and immigration within the US, including materials regarding the Cuban refugee population and some material regarding Eastern European refugees. Subseries particularly focuses on discrimination against female immigrants. Files also include material regarding gay rights immigration and raids on immigrant populations. Materials primarily include case studies, articles, and court reports applicable to Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center's work, but not directly related to it.
    - CIV - Graham #98-1134, 1998-1999, (4 folders) (Box 27)
    - Cuban detainees, 1996-1998
    - Discrimination against female immigrants, 1986-1996
    - U.S. Discrimination against women, 1980-1987, (3 folders)
    - Extension 5 to Lindemann Declaration, 1986, (1-3 of 6)
    - Extension 5 to Lindemann Declaration, 1986, (4 to 6 of 6) (Box 28)
    - Farmworkers, 1996-1999
    - Gay rights immigration, 2000-20002
    - HIV update, 1992
    - Immigrant women articles, letters, studies, 1988-1994, (3 folders)
    - Immigrant women: Cheryl's notes, 1982-1993 and undated
    - Immigrant women: miscellaneous booklets, articles, 1991-1995
    - Immigrant women: public benefits litigation, 1988
    - Immigrant women: women in farm labor population, 1988 (Box 29)
    - Indefinite detention packet, 1999
    - Public benefits paybacks, 1996-1998, (2 folders)
    - Raids, 1997
    - Raids, 1997-1998
    - Raids, file #1 - documentation, 1997
    - Raids, file #2 - people/organizations already faxed, 1997
    - Raids, file #3 - forms for documentation, 1997
    - Raids, file #4 - raids information, 1997
    - Raids, file #5 - articles and miscellaneous, 1997
    - Raids articles, 1998
    - Selugal - workplace raids, 1997 Mar. 28
    - Raids - women, 1998
    - Refugee right of spouse and children to join, 1996
    - Rositch, Irina and Hristo Sabev, 1997
    - Securing Our Borders: Post 9/11 Scapegoating of Immigrants, 2005
    - Sugar cane workers suit, 1989, (1-2 of 4 folders)
    - Sugar cane workers suit, 1989, (3-4 of 4) (Box 30)
    - Temporary protected status - letters, addresses, etc., 1989-1994
    - Trujillo et. al. v. Reno et. al, 1998, (4 folders)
    - General - United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR), 1995-1997
    - Unleash the Dream: End the Colossal Waste of Young Immigrant Talent, 2010 April
    - Women - asylum and gender, 1995-1999
- Legal Files Series, 1982-2003, (13 boxes)
  Series contains documents related to detention centers and immigrant and refugee populations of interest to FIAC. Materials in this series have been pulled from the Detention, Immigrants and Refugees, and A/V series based on their potential sensitive or confidential nature. Files include legal documents such as unsigned affidavits, correspondence with or about clients, medical records, and other statements and potential evidence. Files are arranged in rough alphabetical order.
  Access Restrictions
  The Legal Files Series is restricted. Researchers must receive prior authorization from AI Justice in order to access the material in this series. All other series are unrestricted. Once authorization has been granted, AI Justice will contact the Rubenstein Library directly and provide name of researcher, dates of use, and which boxes may be accessed..
  - Haitians Subseries, 1982-2003
    Subseries contains documents related to detention facilities holding Haitian immigrants and refugees of concern to the Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center. Many files deal with requests for asylum, including legal documents such as asylum seeker statements, court pleadings, and affidavits. The subseries also includes PR material, correspondence, and records regarding interdiction lawsuits. Files are arranged in rough alphabetical order.
    - Air France, 1994 (Box 31)
    - American Airlines, 1994
    - Asylum seeker statements (Haitian boat refugee crisis (2001 Dec. 3), 2002
    - Haitian asylum, 1992
    - Attorney General, INS Commissioner, International Affairs communication, 1994
    - Blood tests, 1982-1988
    - Ceide, Nicolas, 1988 Nov. 4
    - Charter flights, 1994
    - Children and adults stranded in Haiti - profiles and parole information, 1993-1994, (2 folders)
    - Comfort Suites, 2002-2003
    - Congress: oral communication, 1994
    - Correspondence with U.S. Department of Justice (Haitian boat refugee crisis, 2001 Dec. 3), 2002
    - Detained Haitians, 2003
    - Detention documents, 2002
    - District court pleadings I (1982-1988)
    - District court pleadings II (1987)
    - EADs, 1993, 1995
    - Fort Pierce - lists, 1994 (Box 32)
    - Guerrier, Luckner (1983-1988)
    - Haitian asylum seekers, 2002
    - Haitian boat chart, 2002
    - Deported Haitians, Haitian boat refugee crisis, 2002 Oct. 29
    - Haitian packet, Haitian boat refugee crisis, 2001 Dec. 3
    - Haitian boat refugee crisis - legal, 2002 Oct. 29
    - Talking points: backgrounder, chronology - Haitian boat refugee crisis, 2002 Oct. 29
    - Haitian boat refugee crisis, women and children, 2002 Oct. 29
    - Haitian Children Awaiting Visas
      - Blood tests, 1988-1992
      - Correspondence regarding clients, 1994
      - Mexico, 1994 and undated
      - On file affidavits, 1992-1994
      - Speeches, etc., 1994
    - Haiti informational, 1993-1999
    - Haitian issues, 2002
    - Haitian kids, success stories, 1992-1993
    - Haitian packet, 2003
    - Haitian packet, 2002-2003
    - "Haitian Refugees," Appendix A, declarations, statements, testimonies, 2002-2004
    - "Haitian Refugees," indices - affidavits, 2002-2003
    - Haitian repatriations, 2000-2001
    - Humanitarian parole, 1993-1994
    - Interdiction, 1994
    - Interdiction lawsuit, 1997, (1 of 3)
    - Interdiction lawsuit, 1997, (2-3 of 3) (Box 33)
    - Letters from Phillis Wheatley Elementary School students on behalf of Stephanie Jean Baptist, 1993
    - Letters from Haitians arrested upon arrival to U.S., 1985
    - List of asylum seekers, statements, etc. 2002
    - Media, 1993
    - Miscellaneous, 1991-1994
    - Notes on affidavit, 1992
    - National Coalition for Haitian Refugees (NCHR), 1994
    - NCHR - expenses, 1994
    - Outside hearing on Haitian and Cuban immigrants, 1991
    - Packet sent to visa office requesting family sponsored visas, 2004 Dec. 1
    - Post-custody release requests, 1998-1999
    - Ray, Michael, 1994
    - Sidney, Willy (Steve Forester's case), 1983-1989
    - Stanton report, 1994
    - St. Thomas University - parolees, 1994
    - Summaries, 2002-2003
    - United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees, 1994
    - UPL, 1991
    - U.S. consulate in Haiti, 1993-1994
    - YMCA - Houston (1994)
  - Guantanamo Subseries, 1992-1999
    Subseries contains documents related to Guantanamo detention facility and immigrant and refugee populations of interest to FIAC. The majority of materials in this subseries address unaccompanied minors, children detained at Guantanamo, and individual case files. Files include statements, affidavits, correspondence, and other material regarding individual cases and detainees. Files are arranged in rough alphabetical order.
    - Affidavits of parents and relatives of unaccompanied Haitian children, 1995 Mar., (2 folders) (Box 34)
    - Mildred Aristide Packet, 1996
    - Belice, Rosemene, 1995
    - Celestin, Carol, 1994-1995
    - Children's affidavits and letters from Guantanamo, 1994-1995
    - Clearance documents for travel to Guantanamo and information regarding contact with refugee children, 1995
    - Confidential unopened mail, including audio cassette, 1982, 1999 and n.d.
    - Correspondence - children at Guantanamo, 1995
    - Dossiers de Mr. Bernard Jean Pierre Clénès, Coordonnateur Général O.E.R.O., 1994-1996
    - Double backers and returnees, 1992
    - Dr. Joseph Fanfan - medical interviews, 1995 and undated
    - Fater returnees, 1992-1993
    - Faxes, etc. regarding individual cases, 1994-1995
    - Felisme, Olgine, 1995-1997
    - File for contacts in Haiti, 1995 and undated
    - Guantanamo affidavits (clean copy), trip, 1994 Dec. 6-10
    - Guantanamo affidavits (clean copy), trip, 1995 January 18-20
    - Affidavits - Guantanamo, 1995 Feb. 28-Mar. 3 (Box 35)
    - Guantanamo affidavits, 1995 May 30-June 2
    - Guantanamo children - Guantanamo trip, 1995 Jan. 17-20
    - Guantanamo children - Guantanamo trip (flight information, etc.), 1995 Feb. 28-Mar. 3
    - Guantanamo children - Guantanamo trip, 1995 May 30-June 1
    - Guantanamo children information packet,"Sec 3: The Cases of Returned Children" only, 1995 Apr. 25
    - Guantanamo H's-Um's - Reparole and EAD, 1996
    - Guantanamo Haitian minor list, 1997
    - Haitian minors report from Guantanamo, 1995-1996
    - Haitian minors resettled in U.S., 1995
    - Guantanamo Haitians, 1995
    - Guantanamo lists/file, 1995, (2 folders)
    - Haiti report, Karla Pearcy, 1995
    - Haitian asylum, country conditions 1996 (Box 36)
    - Haiti trip - repatriated Haitians, 1995-1996
    - Haitians in Guantanamo, 1994
    - Hunger strike articles and rought draft letter, 1999
    - Immigration related - copies of affidavits used in report, some important notes on how to get in touch with kids in Haiti, 1995
    - Interviews/returnees, 1992 Feb.
    - Investigative report: Guantanamo, 1994 Sept. 20
    - Letter from children at camp 9, 1995
    - Letter regarding children to Congresswoman Meek from Cheryl Little, 1999
    - Letters from Guantanamo and miscellaneous correspondence, 1994-1995 and undated
    - Packet: Raul Hernandez and Meg Laughlin, 1996 May
    - Guantanamo - Haitian minors repatriated lists, 1995-1996 and undated
    - Repatriated Haitian minors, letters (originals and translations), 1996
    - Sponsors, 1995
    - Statements of children for representation, 1994-1995
    - United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) correspondence, Guantanamo, 1995
    - Update reports, 1995 and undated
  - Krome Subseries, 1985-2001
    Subseries contains documents related to Krome detention facility and immigrant and refugee populations of interest to FIAC. Materials in this subseries address abuses that took place at Krome, FBI interviews regarding abuses, and records and documents related to the hunger strikes. Files include affidavits, correspondence, and other files regarding individual cases and detainees. Files are arranged in rough alphabetical order.
    - 79th street incident, 1990 July (Box 37)
    - Krome, abuses, 1989, 1991, 1993
    - Abyse/Immigration Enforcement Monitoring Project (ILEMP)/Krome 1990
    - Abuses at Krome, 1989
    - Krome affidavits, 1999-2000
    - Affidavits of abuses, 1989-1991
    - Affidavits and articles, pp. 1-220, 1990
    - Affidavits transfer (and others), 1991 April 4
    - Krome attorney visit, 1983
    - Aquino, Tony, 2000
    - Concerns at Krome, 1998
    - Contact's cases, 2000
    - Correspondence - Krome, 1998
    - Correspondence, 2001
    - Krome detainee information and affidavits, 1998
    - Ebibillo, Tony, 1991-1994
    - FAT - pack II, Krome, 1989-1991
    - FBI interviews of Krome detainees (1990)
    - Florida Immigration Advocacy Center, mailing record (faxes, email), 2000
    - Krome grievance S.L., 2000 Sept. 7
    - Haitian deaths/transfers from Krome (2001) (Box 38)
    - Hunger strike, Krome, 1991
    - Hunger strike, Krome, 1992-1993
    - Interviews, returnees (originals, etc.), Guantanamo, 1992 Feb.
    - Krome 1989
    - Krome 1990
    - Krome 1990-1991
    - Krome 1992
    - Krome 1999, (3 folders)
    - Miscellaneous, Krome and TGK, 2000-2001
    - Notes - Krome, 1990 and undated
    - Ope-Agbe, Bariu, 1996
    - Krome originals, 1999
    - Political asylum issues, 1989
    - Rape case, Krome, 1991
    - Rape case, Krome, Marie Baptiste, 1991
    - Krome reports, 1996
    - Krome supplement, 1998
    - Todaro, Jeannie, 1990
    - Transcript and translation of cassette, attorney access, Krome, 1985 Sept. 23
    - Krome update, 1999
    - Theresias, Wislaine citizenship, baby case (Krome?), 1989
  - Turner Guilford Knight (TGK) Correctional Center Subseries, 2000-2002
    Subseries contains documents related to Turner Guilford Knight Correctional Center (TGK) and immigrant and refugee populations of interest to FIAC. Materials in this subseries address abuses and conditions at TGK. Files include affidavits, correspondence, interviews and other files regarding individual cases and detainees. Files are arranged in rough alphabetical order.
    - Bouti, Maha Bachir, A 71 858 110, 2000-2001 (Box 39)
    - Client correspondence, 2000-2001
    - Client interviews, 2001
    - Condition complaints, 2000-2001
    - Correspondence, 2000-2001
    - Duncan, Sandrine, 2001
    - Florida Immigration Advocacy Center correspondence, 2000-2001
    - Garcia, Georgina Concepcion, Honduran, A90-414-665, Sarasota County Jail, 2001
    - General information, 2001-2002
    - Georges, Guerlaine, Haitian, A74-942-287, Sarasota County Jail, 2001
    - Hernandez, Niurka, Cuban, A028-27-9797, Sarasota County Jail, 2001
    - Lazar, Madline, 2001
    - Martinez Diaz, Olimpia, Cuban, A73-771-515, Sarasota County Jail, 2001
    - TGK miscellaneous, 2000-2001
    - Paz Tate, Bertha Alicia, 2000-2002
    - TGK report, 2000-2001
  - County Jails Subseries, 1994-2001
    Subseries contains documents related to the Florida county jails and immigrant and refugee populations of interest to FIAC. Materials in this subseries address abuses and conditions at county jails, particularly Citrus, Hernando and Manatee county jails. Files include affidavits, correspondence, interviews and reports and resolutions. Files are arranged in rough alphabetical order.
    - Rike County Jail, 1999 (Box 40)
    - County jail supplement, 1998
    - County jail supplement, 1999, (2 folders)
    - Affidavits, county jails, 1996-1997 (Box 41)
    - Affidavits, 1998
    - Affidavits continued, 1998
    - County jails 1999
    - County jails' conditions, Citrus/Hernando/Manatee, undated
    - County jail, detainees' letters, affidavits, etc., 1998
    - County jails - Florida pending, 2001
    - Jackson County Jail affidavits, 1998 and undated
    - Jackson County Jail, investigations, exhibits, 1994-1995
    - Jackson County Jail, notes: detainees, 1998
    - County jails visit, 1999 July
    - Manatee County Jail, 2000 and undated
    - Report on county jails, drafts and resolutions, 1996-1997
  - General Immigration Subseries, 1988-2002
    Subseries contains documents related to immigrant and refugee populations of interest to FIAC. The materials in this subseries address public benefits litigation and paybacks and raids on the immigrant population. Files include documentation of raids, court documents, audiovisual material, and other files concerning individual clients.
    - Adebayo, Joseph, 1995-1996 (Box 42)
    - Immigrant women, public benefits litigation, 1988
    - Judge Foster, 2002
    - Order Granting Motion to Dismiss, 2002
    - Public benefits paybacks, 1996-1998
    - Rositch, Irina and Hristo Sabev, 1997
    - Raids documentation, file #1, 1997
    - Raids, general, 1997 Mar. 28
    - Raids, file #2 - people/organizations already faxed, 1997
    - Xayrath, Bounpavy regarding medical waver, 1993
    - Children's letters, affadavits from GITMO (audio cassette), undated
    - Unaccompanied Haitians in FL (floppy), 1996
  - General Detention Subseries, 1991-1999
    Subseries contains documents related to immigrant and refugee populations of interest to FIAC. The materials in this subseries address detention procedures and abuses, as well as cases of indefinite detention.
    - Affidavits and client information, expedited removal, 1996 (Box 43)
    - Citizenship, 1998
    - Detention abuses, 1991, (2 folders)
    - Indefinite detention, 1997-1999
    - INS detention, 1996-1997
    - INS procedures, 1993-1995
- General Organizational Records Series,2005-2011, (1 box)
  Series contains booklets from the Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center Awards Dinners and the Tenth Anniversary Dinner.
  - Seventh Annual Awards Dinner, 2005 Mar. 9 (Box 47)
  - Tenth Anniversary Dinner, 2006, Mar. 6
  - Annual Awards Dinner, 2007 Feb. 13
  - Hearts for Freedom Awards Dinners, 2008 Feb. 29
  - Annual Awards Dinner, 2009 Feb. 17
  - Awards Dinner and Celebration, 2011 Feb. 22
- Audiovisual Series, 1990-2004, (1 boxes)
  Series contains promotional/educational videos produced by or for FIAC, documentary footage of missions and events and press conference and news footage. Series includes documentation of hunger strikes and material regarding Haitan women and children. All VHS format unless otherwise noted.
  - Angels of Justice, Y Not Productions, FIAC, 2004 (Box 44)
  - Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center, undated, (12 minutes)
  - Freedom! A National of Immigrants, FIAC, 2002
  - Haitian Children at Guantanamo, Video News International Footage, Miami Press Conference Broadcasts, 1995 Mar. 31, (10 minutes)
  - Interview, FIAC, 2004 Nov.
  - Jose Humberto Herrera, His personal experiences at Krome while being detained, 1989
  - Krome Spc. Picnic for Detainee's, 1995 July 7
  - Krome - interviews, 1990 May 11.
    Oral statements of Krome detainees (paroled recently) Lavidieu Conserve, Molaire Noel, Villa Labrache, Huguette Liberus, Loucius Courageux, Freda N Azaire.
  - Mothers For Freedom Hunger Strike At Krome Detention Center, 1999 April
  - Mothers For Freedom Hunger Strike at Krome Detention Center, (18 minutes 30seconds)
  - Olgine Petit Goave Haiti May 19 for Ms. Reno
  - Press Conference at Krome Detention Center, 1999 March 11
    Subject: Lulseged Dhine, Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center.
  - Press Conference Regarding Haitian Children at GTM0 by Florida Rural Legal Services, 1995 May 22
  - Press, Haitian Children At Guantanamo, Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center
  - Primer Impacto Edicion Nocturna, Presos de Krome Rom pen el Silencio Ricardo Arambarri, Miami, Florida, 2000 19 Oct.
  - RONALD A, Florida Rural Legal Services, (two copies)
  - Sweet Land of Liberty, Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center, 2005
  - Tenth Anniversary, Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center, 2006
    DVD.
  - HRC 4-90 #202, 1990 April
    Testimonies of Refugees, Teacher J.T.; Party for Evenette Mondesia I Farewell Party, Cheryl's Intra, Sony Douyon, Chantale Pierre, Wilsin Datiste, Gagory Smith, Jeannine Todaro.
  - UM interviews, Haiti, Aug 6-3 trip
  - A video regarding the US Government's forcible repatriation of Guantanomo's Haitian children, 1995 May
  - With Liberty and Justice for All? Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center, 2000
  - With Liberty and Justice for All? 2001
  - Women and Children, Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center, YAP Inc., 2001
  - Would You Harbor Me? Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center, Ynot Art Productions, Inc., 2003, (12 minutes)
  - FIAC: You Can Save a Life / FIAC: Usted Puede Salvar una Vida, (3 minutes)
    in English and Spanish.
  - Guantanamo video notes II, Crowing Rooster Arts, Inc., 1993 April
  - Cuban EAD case press conference- photos
    DVD-R.
  - Deportee, Chantal Regnault and Rachele Magloire
    A 20 minute edited piece from the documentary with French and English subtitles, and a 2 minute trailer with French or English subtitles, DVD-R.
  - Securing Our Borders, Post 9/11 Scapegoating of Immigrants, Cheryl Little and Kathie Klarreich, April 2005, FIAC
  - Sove Nou, promo, Kijik Multimedia
  - DVD, "Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center Tenth Anniversary 2006"
  - Luz Marina Cordenas, 2001 June 28
    Audio Cassette.
  - Calls from Haitian Detainees at Krome Camp, re: forcing detainees to sign, 1990 April 15
  - Tape: Ingrid Jose, 1994 March 24
  - Press Conference, Miami Religious Delegation to Guantanamo, 1991 January 2
  - From folder Oversight Hearing on Haitian and Cuban Immigration, 1991, unlabeled
    mini cassette.
- Photographic Materials Series, 1989-1995, and undated, (2 boxes)
  Series includes photos of Guantanamo 1994-1995, Krome 1989-1990, demonstrations and other miscellaneous photos, in black and white and in color, undated.
  - Assorted 1989-1995 and undated (Box 45)
    Includes photos of Guantanamo 1994-1995, Krome 1989-1990, demonstrations and other miscellaneous photos, undated.
  - Guantanamo advocates, 1991-1992
  - Miscellaneous extras of camp scenes, 1994
  - Guantanamo detainee statement trip, 1995 May, (5 folders)
    Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center trip to take statements from children and adult Haitians detained at Guantanamo camps.
  - Guantanamo L.A., 1995
  - Guantanamo Camp #9, 1990-1995
  - Guantanamo Camp #9 kids, 1994-1995
  - Guantanamo press conference Homestead AFB, 1995
  - Guantanamo, various, 1994-1995
    Family Camps 4, 5, 7; Cuban paintings; Camp #11; goodbye party, views of camps.
  - Karla's Visit to Haiti, Guantanamo, 1995 Aug., (2 folders)
    Repatriation of Haitian unaccompanied minors.
  - Haiti, 1995 Aug. 6-13
  - Ship Arauole - SMII, undated and 1995
    Photos were taken sometime between 1991-1996. These photos are related to the Ismae Lawsuit. The boat is docked with 3 Haitian stow-aways held in a cage on the docks. Also contains photos of a plane to Guantanamo in 1995.
  - FLS and other events, office photos, undated
  - Haitian Refugee Center, undated, (1-7 of 14 folders)
    Cheryl Little with Haitian Refugee Center, Inauguration of Aristide.
  - Haitian Refugee Center, undated, (8-14 of 14 folders) (Box 46)
  - Miscellaneous, undated
    Primarily staff on-site.